Welcome back to A-Push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. On the surface, the 1920s was
great. It truly was. I mean, do you
remember back to units 1 and 2 of this
course, where we talked about America
being founded on people living in the
rural countryside? Now, we have gone so
far with so many big corporations that
in the '20s, it will be the first time
in American history where there is more
people living in big urban cities than
in the rural countryside. So, if the
'20s are so glamorous, how exactly can
something like the Great Depression even
happen? Here's your answer with four
reasons. The first is simply
overproduction because the American
economy was so industrial that during
the '20s, it produced more goods than
people could buy. The second is debt
because pretty much all consumers and
businesses were deeply in debt. The
reason for that is that all the lavish
things bought by these people in the
'20s were purchased through things like
credit and not actual real paper money.
The third one here though is a
bank/Federal Reserve failure because
banks were giving out risky loans, had
little oversight, and collapsed rushed
to withdraw their money, and the Federal
Reserve didn't step in to help. And
finally, the fourth reason was the
economy around the world was not that
great. European economies depended on US
loans after World War I, so when US
banks collapsed, loans were recalled.
And with all these four causes in play,
it's like a room full of gas that
requires one spark for the whole room to
go boom. And that spark will be when the
stock market crashes in 1929. Pretty
quickly, the Great Depression will be
devastating. Millions will lose their
jobs, homes, and savings. The
unemployment rate will shoot up to a
staggering 25%. Millions who couldn't
afford food lined up in historically
long bread lines where there was never
enough food to go around, and people who
lost their homes built makeshift
shelters out of scrap wood and
cardboard, which would make shantytowns
known as \quote} Hoovervilles. Families
would migrate all over the place to
search for work, and children would
often go without school. As for the
initial federal response, it will be
quite weak and It would on voluntary
cooperation between businesses and
government. Pretty quickly, when this
doesn't work, America will redefine
itself in the ideas of modern American
liberalism. This will call for the
regulation of markets, social insurance,
and most importantly, responsibility in
the hands of government for economic
well-being. That means bye-bye
laissez-faire. It was nice knowing you.
On the screen now are AP style questions
for this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.